howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
jimrudshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
today's guest on this current episode is
greg henry kiss greg is professor of
psychology at james madison university
hi jim happy to be here hey good to have
you back on the show greg
thanks so much yeah greg is the author
of a new unified theory of psychology
and he's also developed the associated
tree of knowledge that we discussed in
episode
59. today we're going to talk about
greg's idea called the fifth joint point
and i gotta throw a joke in here when i
i first
read and heard about the fifth joint
point i said ah that reminds me of a
pink floyd concert
i went to in 1973 yeah by about the half
time i think we're about
at our fifth joint amen
back in the good old days right yeah man
yeah so
and you know at the highest level the
fifth joint point
is i was able to extract it from the
book is essentially the
very big picture the uh history of the
universe could be summarized in four
steps as matter life mind
culture and metaculture maybe you could
uh tell us how you got to metaculture
and maybe do a little
brief recap you know recapitulation of
your tree of knowledge
absolutely thanks so much yeah and as i
mentioned uh
in a blog i did with john verveigh on
transcendence consciousness
in 1997 the picture of the tree of
knowledge emerged
um and it was actually as i was enjoying
a joint at the time
so i had a flash the tree of knowledge
does get so the joint points do have a
number of different
references and that could be uh a one
fun association of reference
um but so let's yeah let's just track it
out um
so the tree of knowledge uh is a map of
cosmic evolution
uh that maps both reality and our
scientific knowledge of it
um and it maps reality into four
different
uh dimensions or uh or of behavioral
complexity
or planes of existence i use those terms
interchangeably
it starts with our modern cosmological
picture
of the universe starting say 13.7
billion years ago
there is some more modern debate about
exactly that age but
we'll go with that for now and existing
in a state uh we'll call it here a pure
energy singularity
uh then we get a big bang inflationary
period
um in which the argument is is that this
gives rise then to the dimension
of matter so uh in physics matter is
uh you know something that takes up
space time and has
has mass we're going to use the
dimension of matter
uh to be the dimension of three
dimensions of space
uh the dimension of time and the energy
matter interactions that emerge out of
big bang and so then we can then trace
this at the level of the development of
particles
uh into atoms atoms then cluster into
groups
giving rise to stars and galaxy clusters
also inside of stars we get increasingly
complex
atoms and ultimately in terms of the
evolution of the material universe
say over a 10 billion year period if we
follow our little history we get to the
planet earth
uh four billion years ago where you get
these complicated chemical
uh actions and reactions happening uh
and then either seeded by an astro
asteroid of some level
or emerging here on earth we get the
emergence of the
jump into the second dimension of
complexity called
life um and we can talk a lot about what
is it that actually gives rise to these
steps
but the fundamental point about the tree
of knowledge says that life
is an emergent complex adaptive plane of
existence so whereas the material
dimension is largely complicated
we can think about life as
self-organizing dynamic complex adaptive
systems
uh the tree of knowledge makes the point
that these are information
storage and processing systems uh say
with inside the cell
and of course dna rna as sort of
exemplars of that
and they're also cell to cell
communication systems
it's this information processing and
cell to cell to communication
that really plays a central role on why
life represents
a separate complex adaptive plane and i
mentioned that so that we can be clear
as when we get up to the fifth joint
point
uh this point about information
processing uh and communication is key
so then you the the tree of knowledge
follows uh
the trail of evolution into
uh plants and then ultimately animals at
the cambrian explosion
we see the burst of the animal world a
tree of knowledge argues that that's
another complex adaptive plane of
existence
why because the nervous system yoked
cells together
to create a centralized information
processing system and animals that
engage
in animal to animal communication
patterns and then we see the dimension
in the language of the tree of knowledge
mind is the dimension of animal behavior
it's also when we get phenomenological
consciousness emerging
uh through the development of brains uh
and then we trace the evolution of
animals
i know we're going pretty fast here but
we want to get to and then what happens
with humans
is a new novel kind of communication
system
uh specifically symbolic language that
yokes minds together
and then allows us to create capital c
culture
which are shared systems of
justification
these are the narrative structures uh
that give rise to our belief value
systems our propositional networks
how the hell we make sense out of stuff
and over the last 50 000 years we've
really seen the explosion of the
evolution of
the culture person plane of existence
that's the fourth dimension
again we have a novel information
processing communication network
so each dimension following matter
that's life mind and culture
is an emergent dimension of complexity
as a function of an information
processing communication network
that's what gives rise to its novel uh
properties and behavioral complexity
dynamics
so if you follow that line of thinking
um
and you i knew about six weeks to six
months after i
sketched out the tree of knowledge in
1997 uh
that seeing these patterns results in
the conclusion that the 21st century
may well see the beginning of a whole
another dimension of complexity
why each dimension of complexity is
associated with emergence of an
information processing
and communication system that are
networked together uh
and look around in the 21st 20th century
we laid out a lot of those parts
we've connected them together with an
internet uh and now we're really seeing
the emergence of what
we might call the digital dimension uh
to at least reference the infra kind of
information storage
processing and communication networks so
we're
sort of on the cusp of whatever perhaps
comes next
so that's one key feature of the fifth
joint point is the idea that we're
really on the cusp of yet another
emerging dimension of
behavioral complexity or plane of
existence uh it's called metaculture
just as a reference
to that's what's above beyond and
transcending
the dimension beneath it wow thank you
greg
history of the universe uh 13.4 billion
uh
years and uh five minutes well done
yeah it's funny uh you know i work in an
area called game b
uh which i i would say is approximately
the level of your metaculture as we
contemplate
what comes next and i use the phrase
what comes next all caps
yeah uh as the uh i would say i think
almost an exact synonym for uh
metaculture you know
uh i think both of us have this strong
feeling that something is coming
but we can't put our finger exactly on
what right
exactly and game b uh there's an
enormous amount i've been i've been
tracking
i know that i think you call it the san
diego version i've been tracking jordan
hall daniel schmackenberger
i learned then from your guys
conversation uh that
you know game b stuff and i saw the
brent weinstein on rebel wisdom
in your discussion there also you know
2013 2014
stanton conferences um learned all about
that and of course i was here uh you
know down the road
uh having my own vision and they're
exactly there's an enormous amount
of synergy uh and and so for me one of
the things that i realized
um is that the emergence of the digital
is going to fundamentally change the
rules of the game
uh so what jordan hall called the blue
church i just called the old
institutional
uh in inertia and infrastructure that
wasn't going to be able to handle
the accelerating dynamic complexity
that gives that is a function of how ai
and the internet and other kinds of
things are just going to change the role
of the game so
i do think i was seeing globalization
and artificial intelligence and digital
communication
as creating so many new rules uh
and so many new opportunities that the
old infrastructure was not going to be
able to be sufficient
and if we didn't up grade our
programming and cultural code
we might find ourselves in well a
shitload of trouble
absolutely i think that's the other
point where we're absolutely
in agreement uh we both call it the meta
crisis
right uh that's a game b term and it's
your term as well this is a direct quote
from your book
uh well the combination of careless
stewardship
population explosion local realities
clung to as the truth and resource
degradation and depletion end in global
conflict
and the destruction of culture uh you
know
culture has brought us a very long way
right from uh you know the
very first group of humans out on the
savannah in east africa
200 300 000 years ago uh
but uh it doesn't seem to have any
breaks right it just builds more and
more and more and more and particularly
when we entered the modern age
people say when do you believe the
modern age happened i say february 23rd
1694. uh you know and
what the hell i thought that's the event
that was when the
bank of england was set up and uh the
invention of central
banking uh mediated uh fractional
reserve banking
and i would say that obviously a lot of
things are that's a joke of course but
it's not entirely a joke there's a lot
of uh science was just being invented in
the late 17th century people like newton
etc
uh the earliest uh parts of the
industrial revolution
people were tinkering et cetera and then
you add hyper
or not not yet hyper finance but uh
fractional reserve banking finance as uh
basically pouring some lighter fluid on
the charcoal and things really took off
right around 1700 and i would say that's
the world we're in and it's brought us
from a world where
most people most of the time are on the
verge of starvation
50 percent of children died before the
age of uh
five uh human life span was 35 years
maybe on average uh to the world we have
today which is
much much better however there's no
breaks
you know we're going to either cook
ourselves by
burning all the fossil fuels and raising
the temperature to the point where
uh there'll be a massive die off or one
of our technologies will escape from us
it could be
a nanotechnology it could be ai it could
be
crispr uh there's just so many of these
that
uh you know basically what you know we
what we
haven't done is developed kind of a meta
view
about our culture right uh which uh you
know jordan and daniel and some of the
other great uh game b
folks uh basically say that if we have
to catch up
uh to something like wisdom uh that's
equal to our
capacity uh you know you know those who
listen to the show know i'm a little bit
skeptical
of wisdom in some uh high metaphysical
sense but i think in an operational
sense
uh we need to be able to step above meta
uh our culture and and
build it rebuild a new culture uh that
addresses these meta crisis
again in game b talk we talk about a
society that
is uh network-centric so we hit on your
idea that the network is key
self-organizing and we think that may be
a key
difference rather than so much top-down
more self-organizing
uh and uh and meta-stable
yes uh meaning that uh it won't you know
no single configuration is likely to be
stable for any long period of time
but the the metaculture
has got to be able to exist through
these meta crisises
and solve them and uh you know i throw
out the number 500 years
500 years from now things will be so
goddamn different i can't say much about
it but
uh you know if we don't make it through
the next 500 years then we don't get to
uh
you know play the game again and so we
got have to solve these metacrisis
uh over the next 500 years yep yeah
i basically have a complete uh agreement
with that i i think that
you know uh my frame on that is that yes
we this 21st century period
is on this cusp of this metacultural
transition um
the technology is going to be huge the
rules of the game are going to be
different
and we do need something akin to wisdom
uh that gives us a meta
perspective and enables us to have a
meta-stable frame of reference
uh to cultivate that transition because
it's gonna there's a hell of a lot of
difference that's coming
uh the question is if we get too much
difference then we get tip into chaos
of course you get too much order on the
other side it's that sweet spot
that fosters complex flexible adaptive
uh
being and that's definitely what i think
we need to be doing
right now your one of your key tools in
your
uh work is what you call a justification
system
uh and you you say again this is direct
quote from chapter nine
i submit that our transcendental purpose
is the construction of a new global
system of justification
that effectively merges wisdom with
science and technology in a way that
fosters the emergence
of a new global age maybe you could
start out with telling us what is a
justification system
and then maybe a little bit on you know
how you see this
new justification system uh emerging
uh from this meta crisis and this uh you
know this cusp
in uh in the history of the universe
that we talked about earlier
great yeah one of the central insights
of the tree of knowledge
actually preceded it um was what is it
that really transformed us from primates
into people
um and many people will talk to symbolic
language and
a whole bunch of other things and i
think things like imitation
share joint attention i listened to some
of the uh conversations that you were
having with
zach stein there were a lot of setups
for it
but then you get symbolic language
symbolic language is a radically
different kind of form of communication
other animals have parts of it but the
open symbolic language
system that we have and the insight that
i had about symbolic language um
is that it gives once it tips over into
propositional
meaning statements uh as opposed to when
we go from
antelope there to there are the antelope
you create what i call the question
answer dialectic
uh and dynamic um whereby you can
question the truth of a proposition
uh and determine then the extent to
which it's justified
or not uh both in terms of its accuracy
and its utility for the purpose
and you can do this with a pretty low
cognitive load uh precocious kids do
this all the time
why are you bald why do we eat cookies
before dinner
why do we do this that and the other and
you say that's just the way it is kid
okay um but so well what happens then
uh how do people get coordinated
together and the argument is actually we
can take this concept of justification
uh it's a very fluid and multifaceted
concept
and realize that essentially what people
are trying to do is they're coordinating
investment and influence through
language-based beliefs and values that
legitimize what is and ought to be
in other words they serve as
justifications and then these
justifications are networked into
systems of justification that give rise
to narrative meaning
sense-making coordination and really
what we see is the emergence of cultural
codes
um can be thought of as the evolution of
different kinds of justification
systems so i would argue that first
hunter-gatherers are
engaged in an oral indigenous kind of
justification
it has certain kinds of features
face-to-face dialogue
it will narrate certain ways they'll be
probably more animistic
there's not going to be as much writing
and analysis that comes then
next you see the emergence in the axial
age of what i call
formal systems of justification these
are philosophies that are required to
manage
large-scale civilization you have
experts priests
philosophers etc that are have expertise
because of the way civilizations
organize
we're of course much bigger than tribes
uh we get writing
um we get other systemized forms of
technologies like the emergence of money
eventually
and all of these uh create macro
civilization level systems of
justification uh what i call the formal
systems of justification that emerge to
regulate civilization
and then uh where we get have these
formal systems
many of which are dual world religious
built on tradition
revelation authority they get
institutionalized in various cultural
contexts
then we get the emergence in western
europe of modern
science and galileo's the father of
modern science
that's a different kind of justification
system and indeed the entire modernism
with liberal democracy a particular form
of industrialized capitalism
and the scientific modern scientific way
of understanding
the universe that gives rise to uh
modernism
uh which really transforms of course uh
the whole cultural code throughout the
globe
gives rise to our first globalized
system of justifying
and we see that but it's also the case
from my vantage point that modernism
was significantly limited in its
capacity to give rise to a holistic
uh meta perspective of justification uh
it did a great job of organizing say the
stem fields
but i make the point well actually
modern science really breaks down at the
level of psychology
in terms of its coherence um and one of
the things that tree of knowledge tries
to do
is really give you a scientific world
view that solves some of the problems
and then looks to merge with the
humanities and the wisdom traditions
uh to give rise to a much more
consilient uh picture of human knowledge
and i believe that that's crucial
in understanding the kind of meta-stable
uh systems that we need
to use to guide us in this transitionary
phase
yeah it's very good very interesting now
you mentioned meaning
and you referenced the you know john
vervicky earlier and uh
at least in my world verveiki is most
well known for his 55 hours of videos on
the meaning crisis truthfully
i'm not quite sure what the meaning
crisis is do you have any sense of that
oh yeah absolutely um so there's to me
there's two different
powerful meanings of the word um one is
really ever since there have been formal
systems
and probably even before but certainly
we have documented history and really he
starts
uh with the west and the axial age
um so what you get with once you get
questioning humans building
justifications
people need to know why uh why are we
doing what we're doing
why am i here what's the right way to do
these are very
almost inevitable questions that people
will ask
and then you'll get more and more
sophisticated in different kinds of
answers to those questions
and really the history of philosophy and
the history of knowledge systems
represent people's struggles and
attempts uh to answer them
and we've gone through periods of
history um where
the lineup between say what is happening
inside the culture
uh where the institutional developments
are what is the relationship between
other cultures
its knowledge its technology aligns
reasonably well
uh so that you have uh the answers
provided by the culture
aligning with a lifestyle and people
have more or less
you know a sense of meaning and purpose
that's shared by the culture
and feels fairly stable in that regard
um and then there are other times
where there is a profound crisis of
meaning
meaning that hey there there's a
destruction
ancient civilizations uh devolve uh
there's a lack of
sort of a sense of homelessness john
talks about there have been various
periods where
uh there's a fundamental breakdown in
meaning making
so so you can track the history of
meaning both in terms of its search of
it
and periods in which it sort of
flourished and consolidated
other periods in which it's really uh
people have lost it and felt the chaos
of a lack of meaning
and then i think that brings us to our
current situation what i call the acute
meaning crisis
which i believe is we are seeing a
system of fragmented pluralism
uh meaning the state of knowledge that
we are in we're overloaded with
information
but our knowledge and wisdom uh in part
because of the knowledge is so fresh
information ecology is so poor there's
such fragmented pluralism
we have lost the sense of what is true
and good
in my opinion at least in terms of any
kind of
coherent grounding and so i believe that
we're facing a modern
meaning crisis uh and i think there's a
lot of pieces of evidence
uh that would point to that uh
phenomenon great
i love that saved me 55 hours of
watching verbatim
i tried i've tried a couple times but uh
one of these days i'll i'll make it
happen right
right uh let's dig into that a little
bit this meaning
idea if we think about the world before
say 1750
uh the west was certainly uh had a
meaning
uh that was principally religious yep
right
right uh you know had been going on
since
uh you know probably the fall of rome
finally christianity
uh finally pushed the paganism aside
right
there was still a little bit of paganism
left even in the late roman empire
and so we lived in a world that was
utterly saturated with uh
abrahamic religion yes uh up until 1750
or thereabouts
and then uh some of those roots we
talked about earlier in the 17th century
came together in the enlightenment
right and the enlightenment basically
said
well those are probably just stories
somebody you know made up
and they were useful but uh they aren't
metaphysically true right you know we
think about people like voltaire
thomas jefferson of course uh you know
folks of that ilk
and then we entered into the
enlightenment age uh
where uh in some sense there was not a
replacement a one for one replacement
with abraham
uh abrahamic religion rather there was a
sense that
humanity was now in charge of its own
destiny right
sometimes i refer to the enlightenment
is childhoods
and ripping off the arthur c clarke
novel
and uh that seemed to work for
quite a while uh although of course
if we go out look at the world today uh
the enlightenment values never actually
pushed
the abrahamic religious meaning off the
stage
uh it made progress but uh
and in some parts of the world
particularly scandinavia
uk netherlands a relatively small number
of people are actually believers in
abrahamic religion uh
but in much of the world certainly here
in our united states certainly uh where
you and i live
uh abrahamic religion is still very
strong amen
uh so uh i guess two-part question
one did the enlightenment actually have
a meaning
which is now uh breaking up
and uh how does the uh residual
uh abrahamic meaning relate to what's
going on
great yeah so these are foundational
questions as far as i'm concerned so
um so yes there's a complete dominance
basically at least in europe of course
this is our
this particular western lineage um
western colonial lineage you have a
complete dominance of christianity
until you get the emergence of and
indeed galileo is the father of modern
science
um he hated the metaphysical
speculations and wanted
as pristine of an analysis of matter and
motion as possible
and you know generates empiricism and
really what you see is a transition
uh so what is it laplace who tells
napoleon he has no need for the god
hypothesis
um at least that's an anecdote um you
get a transition
from you know and certainly newton
believed that god was instrumental uh
in in all of this and you have rene
descartes and his dualism
but you get an increasing shift over a
hundred year
200 year period certainly nailed by
darwin
and nailed in terms of its emphasized
when we get the evolution of life
hooking on to the physical world you get
a fundamental shift in our understanding
and the authority of not knowing which
used to be in the catholic church and
priests
now gets shifted uh certainly by the
time of the 19th into the 20th century
who are the authorities on knowledge but
scientists you know um
and and the scientific worldview is then
shared uh as the central point of truth
um at least in and then there's a
bracketing of different domains of
science versus religion
and their inner relations i think are
absolutely central to our current
meaning crisis um so you know
kids in my neighborhood you know
stewards draft okay you're learning the
whole truth of the bible
right and then you go to high school and
then your biology teacher mentions well
actually you are a primate
that evolved you know and then the
can hit the fan and everyone has to
dialogue whether is it okay
to learn about the theory of evolution
in school um
which to me is a great example of how
confused we are
because of course part of the
enlightenment was to set up the
separation of religion
of church and state so that people could
be free to believe what they want
but at the same time we are going to
have a massive crisis of
education to use zack stein's term if we
can't educate
our children on the most what i would
argue is the most basic principle of
science
is cosmic evolution that is if you're
going to have
any picture any scientific conception of
the universe
it is that we have emerged from the big
bang
over billions of years uh through a
series of complex
uh evolutionary steps and that's the
most fundamental scientific picture
um so we have a real challenge between
various world views to this day
now at the macro global level uh
basically
and the and what happened with the
liberal democratic capitalist industrial
uh scientific modernist way of thinking
was that that became globally dominant
so now science
and its view really is sort of the
shared knowledge system
now where i come in is yes i'm i like
steve pinker's enlightenment now i'm uh
i'm i'm a naturalist uh i believe uh
that in general the enlightenment has
been a very good thing
i believe we have seen human progress uh
and all your points about the stat
status statistics of kids starving all
of that's unbelievably
true and valuable but it's also now
we've released a train
uh that i think is headed uh toward a
cliff uh and it's
picking up speed uh and if we don't
figure out a way to shift it we'll go
off uh off the cliff and there are lots
of different elements
uh to change the direction of say now
the titanic before we hit the
iceberg and and this is for me one of
our things is that what we need to do is
move from a modernist
view of understanding uh and now we're
sort of between worlds we're gonna let
that modernist view
evolve include the key insights of it
and transcend
that and and in part that's going to
actually be returning to some of the
wisdom traditions
of old and pulling the the good wisdom
that was embedded in those traditions
and merging them with a scientific
worldview
and creating a more holistic consilient
scientific humanistic
uh way of being in the world that's what
my hope is for the 21st century
okay so uh sounds like a part of but
again uh it's a very interesting
distinction
this uh science plus plus let's call it
uh we see that replacing
uh revealed religion or do we see this
as uh as the two operating in parallel
one of the enlightenment
force as you point out was separation of
church and state
and people forget the enlightenment was
started
only 60 or 70 years after the end of the
30 years war
which was the most horrific war of
religion in the history of the west
as much as 35 of the population of
central europe died it was like
way worse than world war one in terms of
uh you know the catastrophe
and so reaction to that was what dammit
we have to be pluralistic about religion
at least the most advanced thinkers
right i love to point people to i think
it's the highest enlightenment document
it's the virginia statute of religious
freedom that was jointly written by
thomas jefferson the author of the
declaration of independence
and james madison the author of the
constant us constitution and it was
uh written in 1779 finally ratifying
like 1783
uh years before the bill of rights and
it was extraordinarily radical where
uh guys like john locke talked about
religious freedom
but frankly all he was talking about was
the different denominations of
protestantism right
uh catholics hell no no catholics
uh you know uh madison and jefferson in
this statute which was enacted into law
in virginia
uh you know explicitly talked about
hindus and anybody
or atheists anyone anyone at all uh so
there was a radical
uh uh pluralism that was inserted into
the enlightenment code
uh around that time and of course then
finally instantiated in the us
uh first amendment right so anyway do we
see
science plus plus or enlightenment 2.0
uh finally pushing revealed religion off
the stage
or do we see the two are going to have
to coexist for
a long period of time listen i i okay
yes i i like the term enlightenment 2.0
uh the tree of knowledge is
uh positioned really and the whole fifth
joy point is really
uh situated sort of as a call to an
enlightenment 2.0
uh there are many facets to this
question so let me break them down a
little bit
let me actually stay with the
enlightenment because i think
one of my big criticisms of the of the
enlightenment is what i call the
enlightenment
gap and by that i mean what gave rise to
modern science
unbelievably brilliant system of
justification that's
particularly effective at us mapping the
material world
and then anchoring life onto that as a
concept
you know and and so you actually get
stem and our stem knowledge systems are
actually relatively coherent
uh they have language games that people
can generally consensually agree on
and we call them the hard sciences
because they actually at least
the foundational insights like the
periodic table of behavior i mean the
periodic table of the elements
things like that they provide a real
foundational knowledge base
my critique of the modern science
empirical
naturalist enterprise though is that it
didn't have the right descriptive
metaphysical system
so that we could get the right language
game when it came to two fundamental
issues
one was the relationship between mind
and matter
okay scientifically how do we what
actually is mind
what's the proper language for mind how
do we do it think about it
scientifically relative
to other systems of justification and
what actually
is science uh and scientific knowledge
relative to
say old older social pragmatic
systems of justification or religious
systems you know so
the tree of knowledge actually uh
attempts to resolve
uh some of the key inadequacies of our
modernist understanding
it offers a language system that both
solves the mind matter
language game problem in other words it
gives you a full
deck of terms and concepts to coherently
map
no or known relationships subjective
objective perspectives
the nature of consciousness the nature
of self-consciousness
and it also through its concept of
systems of justification
delineates the kind of justification
system modern science is
and how it exists in relationship to
culture which is the
broad uh holistic term for justification
systems writ large
so it gives us a frame to understand and
resolve the enlightenment gap
and with a holistic scientific world
view as a way to describe and explain
the unfolding wave of behavioral
complexity across the various levels and
dimensions
we can now contextualize that in a
holistic way and then
turn and link that up with foundational
values
okay moral values and i think most
people would agree that science
at least in its proper you know classic
modern science matter and motion way
is pretty silent on the issue of value
or at least it struggles enormously with
what ought to be
and in order to have a holistic system
of justification we have to yoke is and
ought together
so that we can see what do we value and
the
tree of knowledge and certainly the
fifth joint point uh concept
is that we will have a scientific world
view that is
up to the task of describing things like
the metaphysics of mind
what is human knowledge things like that
which the current system doesn't do and
then connect it to
broad value systems when you do that
from a metacultural view you look across
say all of the religious traditions if
you think about them as abstract
practical codes
you see a huge number of really well
maybe not even a huge number but you see
a lot of moral relational universal
values
things like love freedom dignity
cultivating well-being being truthful
ken wilbur integral theorist talks a lot
about this and how we used to have sort
of a big three of
a quest for true beauty and goodness
um and part of my vision of wisdom is
that we will get the scientific world
view right
and then we'll be able to hook back into
questions of goodness and beauty
which really have been sort of religious
ultimate concern questions if you're
familiar with paul tillich
he talked about the ultimate concern
questions
and i think a lot of those wisdom
traditions concern those
and i'm interested in building a
scientific humanistic
uh world view that embraces uh some of
those
ultimate concern questions and at least
creates an integrated
parallelistic uh frame of understanding
uh to for us to engage uh with them
very very interesting yeah let's dig
into this this is the heart of the
matter isn't it
yep it really is uh you know uh i've
been working on
the mind matter gap since 2014
or basically educated myself on
cognitive science cognitive neuroscience
and particularly dug into
the scientific study of consciousness
and i actually even wrote a program
uh which simulated a white-tailed deer
in an environment that was i would
argue minimally conscious in a a very
very simplistic level
and so this is uh where i i sometimes
push back when people say oh
the science science is limited you know
et cetera but i'll get to your point too
right where i now see your point about
that which is uh
when people attack enlightenment science
i get the sense that they often are
attacking
a straw man version of it uh you know
what might have been taught
in the high school in 1935 or something
right and you know i like to point out
that
science is open-ended science is uh
you know an attempt to extract
regularities
uh at least provisionally from the
universe
uh and and goes into greater and greater
domains
and originally uh as you point out
galileo uh basically wanted to refute
the absurd assertions of aristotle about
motion right that's all he wanted to do
right aristotle just made up some
and called it physics that was actually
wrong
and it's amazing to me it's one of the
great examples of human inertia
for eighteen hundred years aristotle's
assertions about physics
uh were taken as gospel by everybody and
in reality it would take
two days to do the experiment to prove
they were wrong right
and galileo finally did it and uh
and there we are right uh and the other
one that's even bigger
uh was aristotle said some more
intelligent things about biology than he
did about physics
uh but evolution was on the table since
aristotle
until the time of darwin uh a 2 000 year
gap
any smart person could have thought hard
and deep and said oh yeah it has to
all be evolution
uh via uh you know differential
reproduction
and you know as uh uh
various people who was it thomas uh
anyway uh one of the uh
uh darwin's bulldog famously said
slapped his forehead and said
how stupid of me not to have thought of
that right huxley uh was it
yeah thomas huxley exactly exactly uh
because you know when you think about it
has to be true
right it makes it almost mathematically
it has to be true it was sitting on the
table since aristotle
but i guess back no turning back to the
point modern science isn't just
newton plus darwin right right and a
simplistic darwin
uh we had relativity uh which adds all
kinds of spooky strange stuff that we're
still working our way through
the quantum phenomena amen you know
we're literally
uh you could see some you know some
loose and i i
it pisses me off when i hear people from
the uh spiritual world
overstate uh quantum stuff but it is
true
uh that an electron from your left elbow
does occasionally visit alpha centauri
all right
so weird shit's going on in the quantum
range and then the chaos complexity
evolution provides some very serious
practical limits to knowledge
right people that say that science is
you know hubristic
and you know there a lot of them are
thinking these uh you know ancient
laplacian type
models of the universe where if i could
have the position and motion of every
particle in the universe i could predict
future history perfectly
well no you can't right there's
mathematical reasons that ain't never
going to happen
and when we expand the scientific
toolkit to include deterministic chaos
and then complexity and as you pointed
out a whole new level of
uh of universal complexity around
complex adaptive systems
that opens science up way bigger than
these straw men attacks and then finally
or this is where i started where the
work i've been working on for the last
six years
is cognitive science you know at the
frontier
uh really is approaching the point where
i would say within the next certainly
next century
we're actually going to be able to say
how mind
emerges from brain and that will be done
within the scientific
tradition using scientific tools and so
at least the first part of your uh your
your one
your enlightenment gap mind from matter
uh strikes me
as uh already being solved by science
right and uh as we as we know when
people just make up whether it's
aristotle or the church fathers
almost always we get real knowledge we
find that making up was just wrong
right right thor does not cause thunder
right
right lightning bolts aren't thrown by
zeus uh
you know uh the uh the earth goes around
the
sun not vice versa when you make up
uh it's very unlikely to actually be
true
uh when or even approximately true
useful uh when science
understands something you know it's not
absolute truth and
you know it's not science when someone
tells you science tells you this is true
science tells us provisionally and has
not yet been falsified
that we think this is probably how
things work uh so when
we get a theory of how mind emerges from
brain from cognitive science cognitive
neuroscience computer science
ai i think all those will be involved uh
we'll be able to answer
uh your first point about mind and
matter in a
truly scientific fashion right well okay
so
a couple of points there that depends uh
so there's a huge issue of
what are we talking about in terms of uh
okay there's the question say the hard
problem of consciousness
all right about how does the water of
the brain
give rise to the wine say a first person
phenomenological experience
and i'm i'm actually in 100 uh general
agreement with you i'm a scientist i'm a
naturalist
okay um i i do believe that there are
good reasons to be
uh agnostic and hopeful about sort of a
mystical
holistic meta-reality view of the
universe um
but that's that's the my mythic uh
perspective on the world and not
my scientific language game but i
m what my issue is is that
modernist what happened with galileo
when he said oh that's all
okay he created galileo created an
empiricist
language system that actually struggles
enormously
with for example first-person
phenomenology because what he tried to
do
was he tried to get the first person
knower perspective
out of the equation and map it
mathematically
and experimentally which was a huge plus
he shifted our epistemology from first
person empiricism
to a general third person empirical view
and that was great
because that enabled us uh to test to
develop experimental to be
self-correcting
all the wonderful things that modern
science does
but i know from the history of
psychology okay
as they tried to make psychology a
science the way in which
the modernist system of science and its
exterior epistemology
was structured it created a huge
freaking language game
problem in fact uh john vervicky and i
are in the midst of a long
ongoing conversation about the
fundamental grammar
problem the problem of grammar to talk
about say
consciousness mind first person
experience self
self consciousness all of what the hell
these terms mean and
what i point to uh in terms of the
inadequacy of at least a straightforward
modernist system
is the state of psychology psychology is
this shitstorm
of different vantage points with
different language games
and they all compete and they don't line
up and it's like
physics before newton you have a
pre-paradigmatic
cluster and what the tree of knowledge
actually does is it comes in and
gives a conceptual field arrangement
to tell you how to define mind and
consciousness
and self-consciousness properly so that
we could actually all
develop a shared language game of our
terms
okay so for example you talked about you
built a the
deer right you what you did your little
created an ai version of a deer
that probably what it probably does is
it demonstrates um
it simulates what's called functional
awareness and response
right uh in other words does it track
things that moves its environment
and responds accordingly uh to give some
uh
consequence that may be adaptive or
adjusting am i right about that in terms
of what the deer does
approximately though i went a step
further and i built a
arc again very this thing is exceedingly
rudimentary right
that took the major components of what
we believe the brain does
my work is focused very deeply on uh two
things one
is attention uh well three things
attention
and then the uh the uh conscious
uh censorium you know the the movie that
we live in
right and then the linkage to a
hierarchy of memory systems right
and the one i've added which uh amazing
i keep
reading it and it's uh in this in this
literature and it of course there's a
few people that talk about it but to my
mind the most important is episodic
memory yes
uh but there's a whole hierarchy so
essentially i used
a uh i took the leading theory and i
uh as you point out uh psychology is a
show
on most any topic you can find three or
four incompatible theories right right
and so i went through and read about
attention
working memory uh you know the the
difference between short-term long-term
memory episodic memory versus
declarative memory and i just made my
own assessment
of which of these theories i thought was
most likely to be true and then
importantly and when i finally do write
this up i think this will be a
contribution
uh i make the point that the ensemble of
theories that i collected
actually cohere you know and the guys
are creating these individual theories
of let's say working memory
uh weren't really looking at did it
cohere with uh you know a theory of
perception it's a theory of perceptual
memory a theory of episodic memory right
and uh and so my a idea has all these
things in it
uh and i would argue i may be wrong
and but there are other plenty of
scientists in the science of
consciousness
uh arena who i think are with me so that
when we fully
understand this architecture that links
attention uh procedural memory
declarative memory episodic memory
working memory uh etc we will be very
close
uh to explaining the phenomenology of
consciousness with no magic
at all right uh the uh the simple stupid
analogy i like to give
and it's kind of it's a paradox almost
the zen type
cone remember those little flip books
when we were kids uh that looked like a
movie
right you flip the thing and again the
other thing in my model is i use a
quantum
consciousness uh not quantum in the
physics sense but quantum in that
consciousness is fine-grained uh at
about
uh 250 milliseconds per frame
so think of a book being flipped for
four pages per second
essentially uh and that's the very first
one i happen to have seen mother's book
books i was in second grade i still
remember it was just so taken with it
was a guy rowing a row boat across a
lake
right and so you flip the book and so my
view of what is conscious what is first
person phenomenal
logical consciousness the guy rowing the
boat
and that's all it's going to be i don't
believe there's any mystery there
uh i'm a cerulean at one level john
searle the berkeley philosopher of
consciousness amongst other things
he loves to say that consciousness is a
biological
process there is not one thing and he
says think of it as analogous to
digestion
you can't point at you and say there's
your digestion rather digestion is a
process that uses various
components and then the rut corollary
the cyril's comment about digestion is
consciousness is the same and often
often has the same end result
that is what i would say my view and the
view of some others
in the uh brain and uh cognitive science
field we're looking at consciousness
uh that we can get to a substrate uh
that will
explain where the phenomenal
phenomenology of the subjective
experience
comes from uh though you are correct it
would be very useful to develop
a consistent language which does not yet
exist to talk
very very carefully about the
interrelationship between the substrate
and the subjective experience but it
does strike me as somewhat premature
uh to worry over much about that
language until we understand the
substrate
right well my vantage point is from a
psychologist the way i came at it
you know i i was i was tangled up with
all of the language problems
and what the tree of knowledge does is
it provides you a meta-systemic
view that allows you to then interrelate
the theories
and that was my first book my current
book is how it provides a descriptive
metaphysical system uh for our term so
that now
i can talk about what i mean by behavior
what do i mean by mind
what do i mean by phenomenology what do
i mean by the subjective objective
distinction
um and i'm i'm certainly in agreement
with you that i believe that
uh phenomenology uh is a whole brain
uh process and we will be able to uh
decode it i like global neuronal
workspace
um i think information integration's
interesting i love dimasio's work
um all of this that we will be able to
stack together
uh a particular picture which we already
have uh there there's definitely a lot
uh to be said uh about it there are a
lot of complexities
one of the complexities i think people
fail to appreciate um
that got psychology all tangled up is
the differences between functional
behavior analysis
uh neurocognitive architecture like the
brain
as an information processing system it
metabolizes information
but you can do that a lot of that like a
zombie you don't need consciousness
what exactly is the tipping point that
gives rise to
a first person experience of being i
doubt you would argue that there was
anything like to be
that deer that you made up you know so
you have thomas nagel's famous point
what's it like to be a bat
um well that's an epistemological gap we
can never
look directly at another creature's
consciousness that's this is the
subjective objective
uh dilemma of interior versus exterior
to use wilbur's distinction
these are huge uh conceptual
philosophical problems it's just a brute
fact that you can never stare
directly at another first person another
entity's first person experience of
being
so that's that does create some problems
but i think we can box it in
hell i argued for a whole unified theory
of psychology which would by the way
actually
my unified theory of psychology would
essentially absorb
cognitive science inside of it and
organize it
um accordingly um but those are all so i
think we're pretty much agreement
uh in general interesting yeah uh
and again i'll go with cyril you know
cheryl is thought to be one of the anti
uh artificial consciousness or
artificial general intelligence people
he
actually isn't his argument is very much
more subtle than people give him credit
for
uh he you know again says consciousness
is like digestion and therefore it is
intimately linked with our biological
being
right so in the niggle sense what is it
like to be a bat or what is it like to
be a human or what is it like to be
a reptile and i would say i'm also uh
with those people who argue that
type one consciousness uh goes all the
way back at least to reptiles and
possibly
earlier uh you know the sense of like
the consciousness of a deer or a dog
being in this movie in the world right
uh
uh goes goes way back there uh but that
is a biological substrate
and as dan dennett argues i think quite
uh
well that the zom the philosophical
zombie argument is actually
a a fake one that uh
for to be an animal that lives in a
censorium
means that you will have consciousness
that you can't act like a dog and not
have a consciousness it's just the way
the biology
was developed at least the cerulean take
on the
a dandenong argument there are no
philosophical zombies in
animals uh it you know seems to be
i think a very well argued point now
then cyril
does say uh that we he expects some that
things that are consciousness
like could be developed in machines but
they won't be identical
to that which is operating uh in
a biological system and so i've extended
searle's argument
taking his earlier comments about
digestion
uh in the food technology industry and
in pharmaceuticals and in organic
chemistry
there are devices called digesters that
use bacteria
yeast and such to say break down
cellulose into its lower level
components to be then used in chemical
factories
and truthfully uh a brewery
is in sense a digester that digests
starch into sugar
and then into alcohol using yeast
and but those digesters are called
digesters and they're analogous to a
human digestion system
but they're in no way the same thing and
hence my a
idea is analogous to
a human consciousness but it's not the
same thing
and i did not i've not yet reached the
point where i could
put in the material substrate to provide
a possibility a phenomenological
subjectivity so i would say that all my
deer
acts kind of like a actual deer
i would say definitely i did not build
in architectures
uh cloned from my understanding of
humans
uh that might give it a phenomenological
experience
but as does cyril i would not rule that
out
i would say that uh once we understand
the substrate of
phenomenon logical consciousness it's
not obvious to me
at all that uh such things could not be
built
you know in silica and but again it's
not it's an
an answer question and it's possible
that there is some
uh thing that we haven't we don't see uh
there could be a gap there
but it's not obvious to me that there is
such a gap and that
uh you know come back in 100 years it
would not shock me at all to find
phenomenologically conscious machines
right right no i i i'm basically totally
agree
uh with you my my my argument comes at
this from a slightly different angle
which simply is the metaphysical
language systems
uh that modernist science handed us like
you know that it's a materialistic
modern science actually
was deeply problematic relative to the
task at hand
of that's why a science of consciousness
and psychology got
had so much trouble and we can do a lot
better
in the language game of science if we
upgrade it uh and use something like the
tree of knowledge
uh to carve nature at its joints um
and to give rise to a much clearer
mapping
of our terms and their reference points
in the world
i think 100 agree with it sounds like
we're we're basically on agreement
uh i will uh though push back a little
bit on something else you said then
we'll move on to your second point
uh which is uh you know the mythological
aspect of consciousness uh this is
something i run into
all the time particularly in my game b
uh work
where probably half the people have an
integral ken wilbury in background
and uh you know ken's stuff is
exceedingly useful i'm starting to dig
into it now if i
actually have him booked to be on this
podcast in the fall sometimes right
and uh you know his four quadrants i
find very useful the levels are useful
up to a point
but then he kind of goes off into stuff
i go all right that just strikes me as a
assertion
cosmic consciousness for instance uh if
consciousness is per john searle and jim
rutt
a biological phenomena emergent from
meat
that is expensive it's energetically
expensive
it's expensive in genetic material it
serves a purpose
in allowing a dog a deer or a human to
navigate usefully in the world
but there's no reason to think that
there ought to be a cosmic
consciousness nor do i see anything that
is entailed from a biological view of
consciousness
that uh results in something called a
witness
which is a kind i i'm not quite sure i
understand it
i don't know if you may have read enough
of wilbert to understand what his
witness is
there's no entailment of witnesses what
the hell this just sounds like
somebody made up no different than
uh divas in later buddhism or
angels in christianity uh so i would say
uh you you did use the word agnostic and
i'm going to be agnostic
i can't prove there are no cosmic
consciousnesses
but i see nothing about the
consciousness that we're starting to
understand
that would entail any such things right
right so so that for me here's the way i
i i operate in this so
um yeah i actually do believe that the
idea of a witnessing
function uh that emerges as part of the
layered
phenomenology so i actually believe uh
you get
qualia at the level of pleasure and pain
uh that
starts to coordinate the whole movement
of an org
of an animal away or towards something
that's the first
elements and then you get actually a
perceptual field
uh that then is actually the flow into
episodic memory
um is actually well described as a
witnessing function by the time you're
up at primates and humans
and actually a lot of what the
meditative um so there's like what's
called a pure
consciousness event meditators will talk
about this
um whereby essentially the qualia
uh of the experiential qualia of like
redness
uh or whatever would be on the screen
blends into the screen itself so all you
get is a hereness
now-ness presence scene uh of of
existence and many meditators across a
wide variety of different domains
uh we'll talk about reaching that state
and experience
sort of a non-dual oneness the
witnessing function becomes
all-encompassing
it it transforms sort of the experience
of being in the world
and and there are actually very reliable
ways in which people are
transformed uh by psychedelic
experiences by other kinds of elements
where their intuitive sense of their
place in the world their grip
that they have about where they are in
relationship to the world
um becomes shifts from from a more
sort of grounded in one level to become
more transcendent and by that i mean
there's a
there's an expansion of the self but
also a fusion of the self in the world
uh there's a sense of peace a sense of
calm a sense of oneness and there's a
huge amount
of similarities of certain kinds of
transcendental
transcendental experiences and how
people work towards them
and there is something in my estimation
uh to believe
that that patterning in the world uh is
well i'll call it fantastic
and what i mean by that is uh i don't
think that fits
really well in the scientific language
game i think that anybody that starts to
make you know strong metaphysical
descriptive claims about its nature
is off key and at the same time i think
that uh
aw a mystery a possibility of cosmic
consciousness
uh for many people it makes there's
enough
evidence uh for it to make sense for
people to be guided by that possibility
to live their lives about that
possibility to seek transcendental
experiences
so for me that kind of spiritual quest
meaning making um is what sort of higher
religious
aspirations can be and can be very
commensurate
uh with a scientific world view
interesting yeah i'm going to actually i
just recently signed up to be a guest on
my own
podcast uh uh jared james uh who's my
producer he also is also a podcaster
he's gonna interview me
and one of the things we're gonna get
into is my theory of mysticism okay
fantastic
and i actually have a i think fairly
crisp
argument on how the mystical experiences
can emerge
to give you the very shorthand version
uh you know as you know
uh in cognitive neuroscience we talk
roughly about uh brain state attractors
you know the famous default uh mode
network when you're
uh daydreaming uh uh unfortunately
ruminating in depression
and also in the lighter stages of
meditation and then the task mode
networks or you know
give the example where you're for the
second time changing the tire on your
bicycle
you know fairly complicated detailed
thing that takes your full attention
i argue basically that there's at least
three other uh whole brain state
attractors
that represent three stages of deeper
and deeper mysticism
and you know i've done psychedelics i
can put myself into a mystical state
that turns my ego off for 10 to 30
seconds
and it is cool and it is good and it is
useful and it does help you
feel different about the universe but i
believe
there's uh straightforward grounded
scientific explanations for them but
i'll leave the details for another day
let's get to your second big point here
and i think this is
in some sense the biggest question of
all and this is where i think we're in
100 agreement
uh which is science in some sense
has uh taken too much of the air out of
the room
right and science has never claimed or
at least it should not claim
uh to talk about art right it goes all
the way back to hume's
famous is ought distinction and yet you
see people doing it particularly with
the social sciences
right oh yeah you know certain people
misuse evolutionary psychology for
instance right say oh you know men
men have this that and the other thing
therefore the patriarchy is okay
right right uh the uh you know
the
the thing uh probably the what comes
next or metaculture one of the most
important things
is what is a well-founded
cultural scaffolding that sits outside a
science
and direct science for the well-being
of the evolution of our planet and on
into the universe
uh strikes me as of the essence yes
absolutely
um yeah and and so for me this is what
sort of a a metacultural
ultimate sort of system of justification
that
resides above the systems of
justification um
you know you and i were at that daniel
gortz meeting daniel
uh you know hanse fryanak aka or at
least half of them
you know drew out the from the
individual to the family to the
community to the state to the nation
to the transnational all the way up to
the global okay
and then the question is well how do we
allow for the pluralism
of an individual of a community of a
state all nested
and at the same time have some degree of
coordination
and is there a global point of which
would then
really sort of transcend into the
metacultural
is there a global point of understanding
that we can reference
uh to at least create the kind of global
connections that are necessary to have a
if we're going to have a globalized
state it's got to have some degree of
coordination
now i argue that actually yes um there
are
sort of transnational into global values
when you look broadly at individuals
coming together
and creating what i call universal moral
relational
spaces in other words people get
together and they dialogue about what's
reasonable
what are the core values that people
have um nobody for example
goes around explicitly justifying that
they are
full of and trying to do
destructive things simultaneously i call
it
false bad justification now people do
false bad things
but nobody comes out and says listen to
me i am completely full of crap in other
words everything i say is inaccurate
and if you listen to me your life will
be 10 times worse off okay
nobody just even hitler or mao or nobody
justifies those that way
people try to justify by a dialectic of
here is what's
true this is a narrative and here is
what ought to be
um and we didn't need to figure out well
what are the themes
that give rise to the good life uh and
then
how do they transcend across individual
family local culture national and then
transnational global in my book and i
started then seeking well what would be
and i argue that there are many many
what i call you call it coherent
pluralism which i like
i think if you adopt an integrated
pluralism on this you will see
many different kinds of meta values that
emerge
so for example in christianity you see
agape the idea of love of the other
that would be a common meta value i
emphasize the big three that i emphasize
are dignity
which i draw from the unit after world
war ii the united nations got together
developed the united nations declaration
of
rights and although people couldn't
agree exactly why
people had rights everyone agreed that
if we confer
dignity in other words value to people
gave them a fundamental aesthetic value
that's really where the whole thing has
to start so we have to say hey
human a well-lived life is a good thing
and we need to protect it and each
person
than is worthy of respect esteem and
dignity
so that's a foundational value and i
believe it's actually kind of the
aesthetic
human value um and will by the way
connect down in
into things like beauty um then i
if you looked at uh before kovid you
know it's taken a hit world health
organization but the world health
organization
as its fundamental mission was the
cultivation of well-being
at the biological psychological and
social levels
and i dove into that construct actually
sam harris has a book called the moral
landscape
in which he argues that he yokes the
concept of well-being and science
together
arguing that really science's quest for
truth is actually
also can be pragmatically interpreted
ultimately to feedback to help
cultivate well-being of sentient
creatures i then analyze that from the
unified
concept the unified theory and develop
what's called the nested model of
well-being which specifies what
well-being is
at least the elements that go into it
that that need to be
fully understand it and then finally
there's integrity
uh that's honor honesty soundness and
truthfulness
um and so for me dignity well-being and
integrity
uh really kind of correspond to okay
issues of justice and fairness
uh and protection of those elements uh
it also connects to the concept of
beauty
then you have well-being like just
health happiness flourishing versus
suffering misery degradation and despair
and then a which is like a health
concern and then ultimately of science
and truth uh so truth goodness and
beauty
can be cultivated through these value
structures and that shows you that
science is a part of the equation
but it won't be the whole part and in
fact you know to the extent that i have
a conception of wisdom
it really does is about truth goodness
and beauty or
the integration of dignity and
well-being with integrity
in fact that's my byline be that which
enhances dignity
and well-being with integrity and i
argue that that's a
potential or it's a proposition for
this meta-value structure that could
guide
globally guide enterprises while also
preserving freedom
and pluralism and a wide variety of
other things that we want to hold on to
i love it i mean it's interesting it's
astoundingly parallel to the game b
things that we use different languages i
don't think we pulled it together as
well as you have
i'm going to think about that and see if
there's a way to spin
that tagline of yours right into game b
if you don't mind it being stolen we'll
give you some credit for it
no that's exactly well actually that's
what was when i learned about the game b
i mean i was really taken because i do
believe
i believe we're in a late stage
capitalism i believe enlightenment
has been great in general although it
certainly warrants its critics
uh i probably have a little more
sympathy to the post-modern critic than
you do but i also
uh am sick skeptical of it but i do
believe its time is now to transcend our
knowledge and wisdom systems
including the enlightenment reboot and
enlightenment 2.0 that bridges values
and science together
uh so we can guide our way into this new
digital world which god only knows what
will behold
but we better be grounded into something
or else uh the wheels are going to come
off this thing and
you know i may not end up in a happy
place at all yeah absolutely i think
we're
almost 100 in agreement you know in the
game b world the platform in which we
believe the game b
has to exist uh and it's amazing how
all these tie together uh was in fact
this was the
original insight that jordan hall and i
had when we met
for the first time had a four hour
insane conversation
at the santa fe institute uh is that
honesty and good faith have to be the
center
right uh of everything in fact the thing
where we both just like wow we're on the
same page
is uh how could it have come to be
that honesty and good faith is a sucker
strategy
which i would argue that it is in our
society right uh today
especially playing at the highest level
yeah and in a society in which honesty
and good faith is the sucker strategy is
a depraved
civilization amen amen and so and then
the next one this is from my
essay which is probably the closest i've
gotten to laying out my thoughts about
game b
and as we talked about earlier there are
various people's thoughts about game b
but this is mine it's called a journey
to game b
it's on medium and i rate i wrote
game b should operate such that
irrespective of their biological and
social endowments
everybody in game b should be able to
live a life of autonomy
and dignity and i think again that ties
into your dignity
uh i think it implies well-being though
i didn't put it in there i'm going to do
it
but i also added autonomy and something
about autonomy or freedom
the word freedom is unfortunately been
hijacked in some ways but autonomy may
be a better way to
real to say that the more autonomy we
have in our life the better
as long as it doesn't conflict with
other goals 100
actually that's embedded so part of the
theory that i developed called the
influence matrix and it talks about
ourself other intuitive value structures
really arguing that we're
cultivate craving relational value and
social influence
but the process by which we must
navigate that is on the dimensions of
power
sort of competition love cooperation and
infusion
and freedom how do we navigate our
autonomy so we're not
controlled or obligated in a way that
fundamentally constrains us
uh overly constrains us relative to
other people's interests and needs so
uh autonomy is embedded in the system as
a foundational
value if you once you put it into the
calculus of relational value and social
influence
well i think that's a good place to end
this has been an amazingly interesting
conversation
oh well fantastic i appreciate you
having me back and i look forward to a
future conversations
sounds good
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com